Spanish journalism is in crisis.
Everywhere in the editorial boards, people
are dismissed, budgets are cut or worst,
newspapers are being shut down.
El País, the most important daily newspapers
in the country, is not spared.
Ramon Muñoz is one of the journalists working there.
He just published an essay on the crisis,
“Spain, a third-world destination”.
A blunt and pessimistic view on this country's future.
When it comes to media in Spain,
his opinion is just as sharp.
The situation of the press
in Spain is absolutely terrible.
No other field, not even construction, has suffered
from the crisis as journalism does.
None, absolutely none.
This year only, 10.000 journalists
have been dismissed.
And every day other
medias are disappearing.
And those of us who remain,
who still have a job,
we see how our work conditions,
and not just the pays,
but our independence in general, are falling apart day after day.
- Do you experience the same situation here at El País ?
I'm going to avoid your question,
and I apologize for that.
We just had a social plan
that affected 129 of my colleagues.
As I declared before, in other interviews,
I'm not...
No but I want things to be told...
I'm not cut out to be a hero,
and I like my job very much.
With this I believe I have
somehow answered your question.
Every day the journalists still working here
in El País, count their dismissed colleagues.
They know, their newspaper,
no matter its prestige, is threatened.
Different scenery. The El Diario editorial,
an information website created two years ago.
In the Spanish media landscape,
El Diario is a sort of alien.
It is rare for publishers to be labeled left wing,
and to closely monitor the indignant movement.
Juan Lu Sánchez is the
assistant editor there.
The medias in Spain are
more and more standardized,
because it's more and more complicated
for those who have alternative convictions
to obtain the funds to express them.
That is why, most of the companies
that own a digital terrestrian TV channel
belong to corporations very, very close
to the right wing parties.
The print media,
despite its difficulties,
finds money more easily thanks to
advertising of through indirect funding,
such as the institutionnal
funds for communication.
The newspapers remain very conservative aspecially
since the Popular Party is ruling.
And because of this also,
the medias are disconnected from reality.
All the demonstrations we have seen
the past two years in Spain
are definitely against
the economic management of the crisis,
but also against the way the medias
are talking about the crisis.
Javier Gallego is a radio journalist.
He is known in Spain for his debate show
"Carne Cruda", "raw meet".
A show without compromising,
that criticized the power,
and which was removed overnight
from the Spanish public radio,
censured as many other
programs these days.
One can just take a look at the broadcasts
and mostly the news programs
to see where the public radio
and television are heading towards.
They are trying to hide from the people
part of what is happening today.
Some of my colleagues from the public radio
are informing me about the instructions they receive,
they're not allowed to deal with  some topics,
they must hide others, disguise some realities.
Most of all never criticize in a violent way the government
for its austerity policies and its savage budget cuts.
All we have to do is look at this country to see the pride
and satisfaction when people say "Viva España !"
Long live Spain ! The country that beet its record
of unemployment, with almost 4 420 642 unemployed people.
A historical record !
Twice as much as last November !
60.000 more than in October !
The forth consecutive increase !
But of course : "Viva España !"
The country where the only family with a job
for life as a birthright, the royal family,
has a son in law who used his position to make millions in business
with Valencia's and Mayorque's public money,
but of course : "Viva España !"
Oh... Long live Spain !
Under the former government,
we were all very critical with the medias,
the national television and radio.
But if being critical is very good,
we realize what we have lost.
Because things have changed.
Clearly.
For this neo-liberal government,
public televisions and radios
cost too much,
they don't fulfill their part
and should disappear.
But for me, the danger is that precisely because of
this manipulation of the information,
they might loose their audience,
because people reject
a message that is not impartial
and that doesn't represent the truth.
And when the audience decreases,
they have the perfect excuse to say
"we will close it down, it doesn't work,
people don't care about public media".
Strengthening private medias.
This is what is happening
with journalism,
but also within all areas
of the Spanish society today.
Make the public management look inefficient
so that they can privatize it.
TELEMADRID !
How to destroy a public service ?
First, she devastates a public
service with a bad management.
Then she tells us that
there are too many workers,
and that private management is better.
"Very well. Then let someone else
take care of it. I resign"
Then the manager thinks of
a different solution…
"We will do a social plan of dismissals
or shut the television down !"
The public medias are very useful
to defend the social values,
because we are aware of the fact
that the private medias, the big corporations
will not defend these social values.
Since the conservatives parties don't have
any interest in defending social values,
they dismantle the public medias,
they cut their budgets, they drain them
and destroy their credibility,
in order to support the private medias
who follow the same ideology as they do.
The problem is that in Spain we have a dangerous
marriage between politics and journalism.
They are hand in hand !
They defend the same values while
journalism should be criticizing the power
and should always question its actions.
Unfortunately through the financial power
that gives funds to the political power,
journalism is also being financed
so at the end they're all in this together.
That is like a caste, who hates the citizen
who takes the street to demonstrate
because he wishes to be well informed,
to be able to actually participate in the democracy,
and who wants this
corrupt system to reset.
What happened ?
Well, this citizen, that anywhere else in the world
would be considered as well thought out,
is called violent, anti-system.
He is disqualified.
Why ? Because they want to
preserve their statu-quo.
The line that nobody can cross :
in democracy you can criticize as long as you respect the law,
and if not you become nothing less than a delinquent.
What they are doing here is delinquency.
La Razón newspaper qualifies them
loud and clear as anti-system.
Do we look like anti-system ?
And those we support ?
Do they look like anti-system ?
Despite their willing to destroy
the credibility of the 15M,
medias are actually talking about the topics
brought in discussion by the 15M.
The 15M was the first to talk about
the property evictions, the end of free health service,
the budget cuts, the indignation.
All these subjects that are now on the front page
of all newspapers, including the right-wing ones.
They're talking about the 15M
without even realizing it !