We won't step back !
We are going to
overcome this struggle !
GENERAL STRIKE !
Come on, bicycles !
We're going to take
another street !
Go bicycles !
Today we don't consume !
Today we don't work !
Less police and
more education !
We are the elderlies !
We are indignants !
I am a retired woman.
But it's not right to abandon the youth,
nor the children, nor the families.
And the Church doesn't give a shit !
They were only here to protest
against the gay marriage !
And the families are thrown
out in the street ?
Where is this Church now ?
Damn it !
What is happening ?
We don't have a home !
I am protesting because
the bank stole my house.
On sale :
Your hospital ! Your dignity ! Your health !
Public health !
Because we don't have
to pay for this crisis !
Because they're not ashamed
of what they're doing !
We must fight for our rights ! We must continue !
And they won't overthrow us, we will overthrow them !
Please continue with us !
I am now at the Princesa Hospital.
But I'll go back home after.
He always comes...
It's our friend
« el pajarito ». The little bird.
The law specifies that your
right of movement is limited,
that you can't protest,
that you can't go to meetings.
This is called a state of exception.
It's controlled.
I am 75 years old.
Our bank ripped us off.
They scammed us, they stole all
the savings we had to end our life with.
The government let us down,
the bank let us down,
The Public Treasury let us down,
everybody abandoned us.
We are a million
cheated elderlies.
One million in Spain !
RAJOY SON OF A BITCH  !!!
YES, WE CAN !