Since the beginning of the crisis,
budget cuts fall one after another.
Austerity, an insurmountable horizon.
In the universities, endowments are being reduced,
classes are being removed,
education fees are being increased,
and everything is being privatized.
The University of Complutense is one
of the major ones in Madrid.
It is also knows as one of the bastions
of resistance against the governmental reforms.
An incubator for the indignant
movement of the 1st of May 2011.
Ángeles Diez Rodriguez is a sociologist.
She took part actively in the 15M movement.
She denounces the reforms applied in the University.
A new model is being implemented.
It is a liberal model,
one that is supposedly trying to turn
public university into a profitable thing.
This action has various consequences.
Only degrees, in this case
masters and doctoral degrees,
that interest firms,
will receive funds.
Other disciplines like
human sciences, linguistics,
or anything that represents
the general knowledge,
and a foundation for
a people and a country,
will be relegated.
They will become secondary,
and eventually they
might even disappear :
philosophy, sociology,
political sciences...
Because this change of model
is their project.
A liberalizing model,
in which the firms will participate directly
in the decisions, management and
policy of public universities.
At the same time, there is
a deviation of public funds
which are no longer invested into the public universities
and go to the private universities instead .
This way, those funds are
now fueling mostly
the education and training
of this country's elite.
The University of Complutense is now
flirting with the cessation of payment
because of the budget cuts
it has suffered from.
At the same time, education fees
have literally bursted.
The increase of the registration fees
have been spectacular.
Until last year, the students
were paying around 600 euros
for a complete academic year.
But now they pay 1.300 euros.
For non-scientific masters degrees,
that don't involve laboratory work,
they are paying at least
1.500, 2.000 euros
but otherwise it goes up
to 4.000, 5.000 euros.
Most of the families in this country
cannot afford these amounts.
With almost 6 million
of unemployed workers,
that makes it impossible for the working class
and the middle class children
to have access to universities.
4 years to study, 40 to repay.
The educated youth, trained
with the public funds
is leaving the country.
They only think of one thing :
finishing my studies,
and getting away from here.
But I tell them to stay and
fight in this country.
Because if there's nobody here to fight
for change, this country will drown.
Ángeles Diez Rodriguez fights
to defend public university.
Cruz Diez, a young teacher from Madrid,
struggles for public education,
also threatened by
the budget cuts.
For the government it's easy
to cut into the budget :
"we'll remove two hours from here,
one hour from there".
But then, you are the one confronted to the class rooms
with those who are directly affected by these cuts.
I'm the one who sees
Julia who cannot benefit
from math tutoring
though she needs it,
Pedro who just arrived
from Columbia
and could use some support
but he can not receive it,
or Juliana who cannot pay
for her school books.
For the government it's only a cut here or there
but I see those cuts.
I see them and it hurts.
Because here, those cuts have names.
And in my case, as a teacher,
they are children.
And it hurts to see that.
There are three types of school:
private, where you pay for all the costs ;
the contracted school, where the government
and the families share the costs,
and the public school where the students
pay only for their books.
Do you know what the problem is ?
With their budget cuts, they are
destroying the quality of public education.
This is turning the public school into a "ghetto",
only for students that can not afford
the private one or the concertada one.
It's our turn to talk.
We're not demonstrating
for two extra hours of work.
We're doing it because our children
don't have the attention they deserve.
In my high school there isn't enough space,
so some classes take place in a greenhouse.
We don't have access to the library
because there aren't enough teachers.
Cruz Diez is part of the
Marea Verde, the Green Tide.
A group that gathers for the first time
teachers, members of unions and the student's parents.
All united to defend
the Spanish public education.
Last year in my language class
we were 20, this year we are 28.
My dream is that every high school
from the Community of Madrid be an excellent one.
Mine, too.
Join the Green Tide.
The Green Tide gathered a lot
of people, really a lot,
were a lot of wishes, a lot of effort,
a lot of time spent. We did all kinds of actions :
demonstrations, we wrote to the press,
we wrote letters, gathered signatures,
anything you can imagine, we did it.
But we couldn't stop
the budget cuts.
They even became
more and more severe.
The social movements, the 15M movement
had some small victories,
with education, with health,
but non essential issues.
It is hard for me.
It is hard to be positive
about the future.
I rather not think about it.
Because if I look into the future,
I see myself out of Spain,
or in a violent country.
As I see this country
getting worst everyday,
I don't believe we will be able
to avoid violence much longer.
Because people are having
a very hard time.
Obviously, when you get to a point
where you have nothing left to eat,
what would you do ?
Steal.
I believe it's something natural.
Stealing, violence...
I don't know...
I don't see the future
of Spain looking so bright.