"Public health"
The labour unions of the Community
of Madrid's health sector,
totally reject, just as they did
at the beginning of the month,
the guarantee and sustainability Plan
of Madrid's public health system,
announced on October 31st 2012.
These measures imply an aggressive
privatization of Madrid's health system,
by destroying the labour conditions
of health professional employees
and by replacing the public management of the health system
with private, profit oriented companies.
This also implies loosing over 7.000 jobs.
As a reaction to these measures,
we now announce the call for a general strike
in the health system of the Community of Madrid,
that will be conducted in the next few days.
You look great !
PUBLIC HEALTH...
… WE DON'T SELL IT, WE DEFEND IT !
The government is determined
to continue these measures
to adjust budgets
to low resources.
That means they want to privatize
some public hospitals from Madrid
and transform others
into specialized centers.
They are dismantling the public
health system as we know it.
Our only wish
is that they don't
privatize hospitals again.
Money here !
Money there !
First the public !
Then the private !
There will be less employees
and less quality,
because they also reformed education
and now people are less trained.
The resources will be affected
because health cares will be
taken in charge by private companies,
and every private company
needs to make profit.
Turning health into a firm,
turning patients into clients,
and their treatments could become
just something profitable or not.
That's unacceptable.
All those who want to speak,
all those who have something to say,
can come here !
There is a microphone.
Next Tuesday they will dismiss
1.400 people in Marañon Hospital.
They will let go 1.400 people.
Be aware of that !
A new executive
for the health system.
This plan has already been applied
in a Spanish hospital,
the hospital of Alcira,
in the Community of Valencia.
The hospital had to outsource its services
and there were no ambulances anymore,
the hospital couldn't pay for ambulances,
nor its therapy oxygen, nor its medicines.
I remind you that some employees are
occupying the Gregorio Marañon hospital.
- Let's set them free !
There are two more minutes left.
Who wants to make use of it ?
NO TO BUDGET CUTS
Works Council Gregorio Marañon
It's been five days since we are doing this,
we're all exhausted.
I have never been under so much stress
on a picket line.
The truth is that this is very stressful,
to be able to unite our forces in this hospital.
I am only a staff
representative in a hospital.
But I know that my colleagues and I
sent a message to our union leaders,
they must make an effort to unite
the combat in the health system.
And they must do that now.
They must make an effort
to make this possible,
to make the coordinators, the platforms,
the groups or whatever,
say the same thing.
One more thing.
There have been some discussions,
that will be brought up again at the 3.30 p.m assembly,
on the role of unions.
Keep the unions out of this.
Look, this is an internal matter, and the unions have guided us,
they have supported us and I am very thankful to them.
Because we are not able to organize ourselves
for something this important,
and we pretend to do this alone.
That doesn't make any sense to me !
For those who don't like unions, well,
try to organize things differently,
but as we are not organized yet,
I wish you good luck.
Thank you very much.
"Budget cuts in health kill"
Yes Marta, we are live at
the Medical College of Madrid...
This is absolutely extraordinary...
YES, WE CAN !
As I said, today,
it's a very important day.
For the first time,
a strike was conducted by doctors.
We, doctors, have never really liked strikes,
we don't know how to do it,
we are not professionals,
we're not a labour union.
And we don't know
anything about strikes.
It pisses us off
to go on strike !
And mostly : an unlimited strike
is a difficult strike.
But we are in this. And I'm sure
that we did the right thing.
We did what we had to do.
We started an unlimited strike and we have
to walk out of it with our heads held high.
We must keep our strength !
We have to continue until
they ask for negotiations.
People have to see us on TV,
down in the streets.
We have to keep explaining people
that we cannot agree with this reform.
We have to make them support us,
to make them join our demonstrations.
So that everybody understands that
this strike is not meant to annoy anyone.
We do this because there is no other way
to explain them what we really want.
PATIENTS ! LISTEN !
THIS FIGHT IS FOR YOU !
The spirit of the 15M
is within the meetings,
neighbor meetings, hospital employees meetings
or education employees meetings.
This spirit is still alive.
Now it's not the 15M anymore,
it's far bigger than the 15M.
Colleagues !
This meeting will end now.
I invite you all to the
general meeting in Sol,
that will take place next
Sunday at 12 a.m here.
This assembly is always the place for us
to do what we are doing now,
to talk about what we want to talk about.
To claim what we want to claim.
And to complain about the thousands of things
that we are allowed to complain about.
Good luck to you all
and see you all next week.