I am Ángeles Diez Rodriguez,
I am a sociology teacher
at the Complutense University.
I participated in the birth of the movement,
or the symptom,
or the hope the 15M
represents for this country.
The Wert decree, which is a law
for the education sector,
affected it on every level :
primary, secondary and university.
In the university's case,
this law established a new model.
A liberal model that tries to make
public university "profitable".
My reaction to that was :
"how can we react in the university ?".
We made a call with four other people
from the political science college,
and we convened an assembly.
A horizontal assembly.
As the labour unions weren't doing anything
about it, we convened the assembly.
And we started talking
about what was happening.
we decided to get together in a
permanent assembly called the Workers Platform,
not an official assembly, because nothing
was made official, but following the 15M model.
We didn't want to become official,
we just wanted to put pressure on the unions,
to be united, to meet from time to time.
Little by little, step by step we became a resistance.
We try to analyze the 15M
as if it were a typical movement.
From what I see, it's not a movement.
I call it a symptom.
A symptom that responds to a trauma,
unsolved by the transition.
And that trauma is related to the civil war
and all the problems related to it.
The transition was only a fiction,
an illusion that made people think...
I was very little but my parents,  for example...
it made them believe that they could have democracy back,
that institutions could
really be changed,
that the land could be shared,that there would
be work and every right could be secured.
And we realized it couldn't,
it wasn't like that.
When the crisis began in 2008, people were striken
by a very strong economic depression.
Despite that, the 15M went out on the street
with a political claim: "they don't represent us !"
And to me this is very important because
it wasn't a corporative claim saying
"I've just been fired",
or "my rights are being taken from me".
The people went out on the street with the idea of :
"they are calling this democracy, but this isn't one"
The young people now don't have homes, they don't have
jobs and probably won't have a future.
But they do have something that the other
generations, not so young, don't have.
They have their youth.
And that youth is an asset that allows
them to get out of this country,
to fight, to have enough energy
to turn around this country.
But there is an entire generation
of 50 or 60 year olds,
that are left without a job
and with a family to support.
That generation is being
murdered by this model.
The situation is very complicated to me,
because on one hand I have to tell the best
students that they won't find a job here,
but on the other hand, from a political point of view,
I tell them to stay and fight here, in this country.
Because if there's no one here to fight
for change, this country is going to collapse.
I think the best solution
is the claim :
"we can change things
if we unite and fight"
The best thing the movement has given
to older generations and to my generation
is the feeling that
everything isn't lost.