I am Alberto Garzón Espinosa,
Congressman for the United Left party,
an economist, and I represent the Economy,
Finance and Budget Commission in Parliament.
I am also an activist of the 15M movement
and of social movements for real democracy.
Saying that the financial entities need to be rescued
is a political and ideological choice.
In order to save the financial entities you must
guarantee that they can pay the debt.
To guarantee that they can pay the debt, wrong austerity
measures and budget cuts are imposed.
But the real purpose of all this
is to change this model of society.
Let's say that the cuts are just an excuse.
The goal is to change the model of society,
by establishing a less developed economy
that could be internationally competitive,
in a world where there's a productive and financial globalizing
and where we all compete with each other.
Many are guilty.
Many are responsible.
We have names, names of individuals
but also institutions, like political parties,
that consolidate this broken model.
And most of all we have to keep in mind
that capitalism itself is at death's door.
Capitalism is collapsing and with it,
all those who supported that vision of capitalism,
the need of a real estate bubble,
the need of living off of constructions.
All those who took part in this illusion
and created the real estate bubble,
are responsible for having maintained
this model and for the situation we are now in.
There are people responsible among
the politicians and among the bankers.
There are others at fault but most of all,
it is the internal dynamic of a system.
An irrational system that needs to grow,
to grow and to grow again and again.
In Spain the only way they found to make
capitalism grow, was construction.
So capitalism needs corruption, connections,
client networks, in order to survive.
I live in Málaga, in the South of Spain,
in a very humble neighborhood.
In front of my house
there's an organization
that gives a thousand sandwiches every evening
so that people have something to eat.
Those people
are not beggars.
Let's say physically they don't look like beggars.
They are people like you and me.
We could be there too, waiting in line,
because poverty has a different face now.
The middle class is disappearing and
the population is quickly getting poorer.
And the worst of all is that
the government doesn't do anything.
This is a critical situation, people are hungry,
people kill themselves because they loose their homes.
A social emergency situation, maybe not as bad as
in Greece, but we're heading towards the same direction.
And this is why we have to be radical
in an etymological way : we must go to the roots of the problem.
Because if you only make up for the problems,
then you become an alibi.
We have a structural problem here
and we need to solve it starting with its roots.
We need for the financial system to be public,
same as for the housing management.
With all the empty buildings we can have a public
housing program with a rent less than 30% of the income,
so that people can have access to a home,
which is now a major problem.
But in order to do that,
we have to let the banks collapse,
then nationalize them and forget
about the private debt.
This could lead to severe consequences,
for Germany, for France
and for the international financial system.
But we are in a critical situation
where the priority is our families,
the priority is the people not the banks
and not rich people's businesses.
History in Latin America for example,
showed us that you can break up with the IMF
and with the international institutions
and that you can create an alternative
economic and political system.
A new Constitution and a new
kind of economy.
We can do things, we can put resources
in the hands of the people.
But we need a first step.
The first step is gathering strengths.
People have to be aware of the fact
that this is their project,
not just a theorical project and
they have to make it their own.
In situations like this, history of economy has
unfortunately given us some bad examples
of very serious crisis that in some
cases ended up with a war.
But I think we've learned a lot from history
and we won't do the same mistakes again.
We are not Germany
nor are we Europe of the '30.
We are more like Latin America in the 80's and 90's,
that broke up with the international institutions
to build a democratic project.