I am Carlos Taibo, a political science teacher
at the Independent University of Madrid.
For many years I've been closed
to the alternative unions movement,
and lately to the 15M movement,
about which I wrote three books.
The phrase "Spain is a great country", has always been repeated
by different Spanish Prime Ministers,
aspecially in times of crisis.
What surprises me in that phrase
is the collective impetus it implies,
in a country where the collective dimension
has always been marginalized, annihilated.
Rhetorically speaking, we invoke the "collective" for the purpose
of a general mobilization in the economic field.
The myth of a "great country"
is based on other mythes :
the myth of a peaceful, wonderful transition
that produced salutary effects.
the myth of the European Union that only brought
money, prosperity and freedom to Spain.
the myth of NATO, portrayed as the great
protector of freedom in the world.
or the myth of the neoliberal speech,
as the central element of an economic
system that has obviously collapsed today.
What I notice from all of this is
that many Spanish citizens
have had the opportunity in the past few months
to start questioning those mythes.
In spring 2011, five or six major elements
were joined together in an almost magical way.
The first, obviously, is the crisis. A second element,
the protests generated by the crisis in the universities.
Third, the precise agenda of May 2011 with
some dull provincial and mayoral elections.
Forth, the symbol of the Arab spring,
which I believe is more important that it seems.
Fifth and last element is the background work
done by the alternative social movements.
Without this work the 15M movement
is literally unexplainable.
unexplainable even if I agree that this work alone
is not enough to explain a much more complex movement.
I believe it's the junction of these five elements that explain
the appearance, that I must confess surprised many of us,
of an extremely vital movement. A movement that was distinguished,
in one of its essential dimensions, by the absence of any label.
People that militated here, could also militate
in parties, unions or other social movements,
but they had decided that there
weren't going to be any labels here.
The scenario became much more
complex starting from June 2011.
When the movement decided to dismantle
most of the campings in the occupied places,
and turned to a form of popular assemblies
in the neighborhoods, cities, villages.
The dimension of "relegated" young people
that caracterized this movement's first steps, was over,
in exchange for a much more complex scenario
both in a generational and in a social perspective.
It seems to me that this form of action,
more humble, less attractive for the medias,
makes the popular assemblies
even more interesting.
Polls show that the movement
hasn't lost people's support.
This is very interesting because I think that the movement
has become more radical during the past year.
Generally a radicalized movement usually looses
its popular backup. But it was not the case.
This movement is clearly
more radical today but
probably because of the crisis and the budget cuts,
the population is still supporting it.