I am Enrique Dans. I am a teacher at
the IE Business School. I'm 47 years old.
In Spain, we have several years
of activism in the technological sector.
There were a lot of strong reactions
on Internet against laws,
against the social and
information service law,
against the license-fee, asking for
flat-rates for example.
These movements have been developed
over the years on the Internet.
And people now talk about it on the Internet,
posting things and sometimes it reaches the medias.
But their attempts failed
to evolve into street protests,
even for the most important ones.
The Sinde law was like a detonator to me.
It happened after those years of activism
and made people see that politicians
don't respond to people's needs,
that they theoretically represent. Instead
they defend the interests of an economic lobby,
in this case the copy-right lobby,
the lobby of the "artists".
This law appears as a liberty
killer and dangerous law,
that allows them to shut down any web page.
So there was a strong reaction to that.
From that point on, a movement
started, to which I contributed,
that we called, "Don't vote for them", don't vote
for the parties that support the Sinde law.
In the "No les votes" group we were actually
six or seven people, and we weren't people of the street,
We were people of the Internet :
there were two teachers,
three lawyers, one new
technologies business owner.
People you don't expect to organize a street
demonstration because we didn't know how to do that.
But we were very active
on the Internet.
And then we went to this demonstration,
I think we all went.
but after we were more
in a position of observers.
I was interested in the influence of technology
on all of that but nothing more.
I was first surprised by the number of people present there.
Then, by the ability of organizing things,
I found myself in a very organized demonstration
in which you could find all kinds of people,
there were people responsible for organizing.
And all that crowd of course ! I went to Cibeles
where people were going to Puerta del Sol !
It was not really a moving demonstration
but more an occupying demonstration.
I had never seen
a protest like that before.
And then, I had the  pleasant surprise of seeing
a great diversity of people there.
I am a teacher in a business school,
I am a liberal,
not a radical one, not a conservative,
but I tend to be liberal.
I found myself there next to people
from anarchist movements, next to communists...
There were people of all ages...
students from my business school,
people from the right wing, left wing,
a little bit of everything. That really draw my attention.
I think Internet has a lot of influence
on democracy.
We have to keep that in mind while thinking
about the evolution of democracy.
That doesn't mean we are ready
to go from a representative democracy
to a direct, participative democracy.
I don't think we are there yet.
But I do think that Internet is something that allows
us to collect people's will.
And then, another very important element is transparency.
Internet allows transparency.
And that's what I want as a citizen. I want those who
represent me to do it an a completely transparent way.