My name is Elvira Méndez Pinedo,
I work as a law professor at the University of Iceland,
I just published an essay called
"The vikings' revolution - the citizens' victory".
In October 2008 Iceland
was in a state of shock.
In a week or ten days, we went from
being paradise on earth,
the country with the highest human developmental index in the world,
with an enviable health system, education,
I won't mention the social services because they are not
even as generous as in other Scandinavian countries.
So we went from being a leader of
the Western world, to bankruptcy.
How did our financial system crash ?
The three major banks, 85% of the
national banking, went bankrupt.
and all the sudden the Government and
the Parliament let us down.
Let's say that this was a financial crisis that
quickly turned into an economic crisis,
a political crisis, a social crisis :
an existential crisis.
Why do revolutions work ?
Why did it work in Iceland ?
First there's the responsibility of the political,
economic, and financial elite of this country :
We must ask them to take that responsibility
and not allow their actions to remain unpunished.
And then, more importantly, the role
played by the active citizens, that got involved,
that decided it was no longer enough to stay
at home and vote every four years.
In Iceland, the average age is 36 years old.
It's a very young country,
with a high technological and internet education.
93 to 95% of homes have Internet.
This level of access to information
and of technological education
means that an online project
can represent the entire population.
The project of Constitution was first written by consensus,
by an assembly later called the Constitutional Council,
and then directly submitted
online to citizens.
This project was submitted online,
so that everybody could update it on Twitter,
on Facebook, as if it were an open
code system, like Wikipedia.
There was no such thing as an Icelandic paradise
before the crisis, nor an Icelandic hell after that,
nor the economic miracle
as they sell it to us now.
There's light and shadow, things that
work well and others that don't.
But the most important thing is that
we citizens, took control of our destiny.
It proved that it's possible
to change things politically,
that we can demand this responsability, this change
of course and this active role of the population,
but we have to work for it.