My name is Pilar Goytre. I am 65 years old
and I just retired.
I have three children
and three grandchildren.
I dedicate myself today
to the Yayoflautas movement.
I am happy to be a Yayoflauta. We'll fight to find a way
out of what is happening in this country.
My father was a military and my mother
didn't work, she stayed at home.
We were nine brothers and sisters
and we are all still alive.
Since we were a lot in the house,
and my father was only a military,
only the boys
got to have a career.
There was not enough money to allow girls
to have a career so we had to look for work.
I studied to be a secretary and finally
things turned out quite well for me.
I started to work for a lawyer,
then I worked for El País for 18 years.
After that, for about 20 years...
no, less... 18 years,
I worked for a cancer
treatment center.
I can talk about my Franco period.
I only got to see the end of the Franco period.
I was still little and I remember
people still had ration cards.
You had to go with the card
and they gave you food.
When we went to the movies, they made you see
the "Nodo" before the movie started.
There was no television but you had to see the "Nodo" before
you watched the movie, whether you liked it or not.
Franco had a dam built, Franco
was fantastic, whatever !
He was such a brillant guy, he was so nice !
It was endless,
every time you went to the movies
they were showing this.
Therefore you were surrounded
by propaganda.
In my house we couldn't talk politics.
It was better to avoid it.
We, the younger ones were more left-wing
while the older ones were right-wing.
And we were always arguing about it !
So we preferred not to talk about politics and religion.
I was older when Franco died.
I was already working for
El País, I remember that.
To me and my group of friends
it was a great joy.
It was a moment of liberation. Besides the uncertainty
for the future, I think it was a moment of liberation.
We weren't afraid anymore. That fear
we all had was over now.
We didn't know what would happen
but we had to go on.
It was a little bit like a revolution.
A social revolution !
So it was an interesting time,
political parties started to be founded,
we had the first elections in Spain, the first democratic
elections that Adolfo Suárez won.
The truth is that all of us took
a deep breath, we grew up !
Spain was changing, it wasn't that grey and sad
country anymore, as it was during the Franco period.
Light was coming in
from all around us.
What happened after, I think
politicians didn't even realize it,
maybe because of the lack of experience
as we hadn't had democracy before,
politicians didn't have that experience.
Political parties didn't know what to do,
and I think they didn't know
how to look a little bit further.
They saw the spectacular moment :
the moment of freedom, of going forward,
of economic growth,
everything was fantastic.
But they didn't think about after.
That's why we had this crisis
that we couldn't handle.
I think that the
politicians were wrong,
the right-wing ones and the left-wing ones.
They all did things wrong.