I am Ramón Muñoz, I've been a journalist
for more than 20 years,
I generally write in
the Economy section.
I work for El País,
and I just wrote a book that's called
"Spain: a third world destination",
where I expose serious
problems of Spanish society.
Everybody says that the Spanish crisis
is due to the real estate bubble.
I say the real estate bubble is not
a cause, but a consequence.
It was the only way left
for Spain to grow,
and we grew a lot.
Even today, real estate is all we
have left to grow.
Because we have no industry.
I believe that's the origin of this crisis :
we dismantled all our national industry.
We absolutely don't produce anything.
Our great international firms, that everyone
here is bragging about, and that you all know,
such as the famous
Inditex, Zara.
It's a very famous brand, but it doesn't produce
anything in Spain. Absolutely nothing !
Sooner or later, this creates an illusion :
if you don't produce anything,
everything is imported low cost from
abroad. And for a while, it works.
Until reality gets to you. The truth is that
if you don't have any production,
sooner or later, you will have the same
problem as Spain : everybody becomes unemployed.
Property eviction is the most painful
phenomenon, which shows that
Spain, as I say in my book,
is heading towards the third world.
This is exactly what happened
in some countries in Latin America,
where people ended up living
in substandard places
for which they don't pay taxes,
and well... shantytowns, "favelas".
I think the same phenomenon
will happen in Spain.
I may seem alarmist.
When I mention third world, I don't have in mind Africa,
with children covered with flies.
It's poverty that every Spanish
or French tourist can see
when they go to South America for example,
or in some Asian countries.
There you can see people with a higher life
standard than what we have in Europe,
but next to that you see the "favelas"
or the shantytowns where nobody wants to go.
But that's where the majority is.
We experienced this situation in Spain in the 60's,
we called it the shacks.
I think we will go back
to this situation.
It sounds hard, it sounds alarmist,
some even call me apocalyptic.
But I invite them to look at
what happened these past four years.
Capitalism isn't afraid anymore,
that's for sure.
This is why we started
to decline, not just in Spain,
but in the whole Western world,
on our labour and social rights.
This crisis, this brutal recession,
I don't think it's a crisis but a true depression
that will go beyond the one of 1929.
It may be the perfect excuse to recreate
the 19th century society,
a society of rich and poor people, with wifi and
smartphones, but still with rich and poor people.
I don't believe that a devaluation is a solution,
devaluation only leads to economic depression.
I don't believe in the Keynesian
solution with more public expenses,
because you need to have this money
and nobody will loan it to you.
And I don't believe
in the utopian solutions either,
thinking that if you go to the street,
like Puerta del Sol,
and agitate your hands,
everything will be solved,
because the rich people will feel sorry
for you and they will pay for your living.
As I see things, there's no
way out beside resignation,
and knowing that we'll go back
to a poverty we are not used to.