My name is Valentin, I'm 21 years old.
I've been in Spain for four years.
I militate for "Juventud sin Futuro" and I'm studying
political science at the Complutense University.
There's no doubt I was
influenced by my parents.
My mother is a teacher and she
has always been very sensitive
to all the movements for the preservation
of the education's good conditions,
or at least those I believe to be good :
public, opened to everybody, free.
Since I was very young, my mother took me
to demonstrations, to these kinds of protests,
and this is how I ended up participating in France to the movement
against the CPE (First Job Contract).
The movement against the CPE had a real great
impact on me, because I was 15 at that time.
It was the first time I saw
occupied high schools,
teachers and students
together in the street.
The demonstrations against the extreme-right-wing
in 2002 had an impact on me too.
I was young at that time, I was 11 !
I was 11 but I remember it well,
all those people in the street...
I think all this contributed to
my interest for political theory,
and then I tried to find a daily practice,
a practice that could change things.
I graduated from high school in France,
I was in an international high school,
a bilingual high school
with Spanish classes.
I graduated with a good
knowledge of Spanish
and I thought to myself
"why wouldn't I use it" ?
When I came here to the university,
three years ago,
I used to pay 600 euros
for an academic year.
This year, out of the ten classes
we're supposed to take a year,
I only took seven and I'm already
paying 900 euros of university fees.
Meaning that I'm paying 300 euros
more with three less classes.
That's why I can't pay for an apartment
so I decided to occupy one.
There are many new structures
that are created, social centers for example,
and also many others that are occupied
to give people a place to stay.
That gives a housing solution
to people that have no alternative.
People have to get used
to living with less things,
because life standards
decreased a lot.
People can't live as they used to,
that's for sure. And it's true, I think,
that people are trying to find an answer,
a solution to this situation,
so that they can live not only
in dignity but even in happiness.
I don't think the solution is going up in the mountains
to raise goats with two coats and one pair of boots.
But I do think the real solution is
sharing everything we can have,
everything we own, everything
we create, everything we know.
So I don't know, what I would like
very much is quite difficult to do.
At least what I try to do personally and with
the others is to give all the necessary strength
to this parallel organization,
this social and political organization.
Meaning that we try to defend a maximum of things
that they are trying to take away from us.