Neighbors !
Listen !
We are at war !
And we will keep fighting !
So that nobody will be homeless !
That's what the Constitution says :
everybody should have a home !
So come here and sign ! Sign !
Sign !
We've been here for a month.
All this was organized because we had a lot of colleagues
who have seen their homes taken away from them.
we decided to come here,
in the center of Madrid,
because all the banks are here.
It worked very well because
more and more people are coming.
It was the only thing we could do.
This is our struggle against the banks,
we try to stop our colleagues from being evicted,
and we continue so that they don't have
their homes taken away from them.
Don't let them fool you, they are lying !
The bank is lying !
What they want is to
keep earning more millions !
Come on and sign !
They're taking away their apartments !
They're throwing them on the street !
Come on and sign !
Madame, sign, that doesn't cost you anything
and you'll be doing a great thing.
Because every little bit helps.
Come on and sign !
My son in law and my daughter
are both unemployed.
they have 680 euros
a month of unemployment,
but they have to pay
700 euros of mortgage.
So they came to live with me
because they have no other choice.
But the problem is that,
if they don't pay the mortgage,
we stood security for their loan,
my son in law's parents and us,
and if the bank doesn't get the money,
they will take our apartment,
and if it's not enough
they will take another apartment,
until it covers for the debt.
And if it's still not enough,
the debt continues.
It is a social injustice.
Not because I say so,
but because the European Commission said so too,
and the Spanish judges said so,
the lawyers and the police...
People now are starting to realize
the truth about this problem.
A woman just killed herself !
And that is the government's fault !
Let them hear that in France, in Germany,
let them hear it everywhere !
But they are murdering people
because of the fucking banks !
We won't forget, we won't forgive.
They are murdering people,
there are 200 deaths so far this year !
Do you hear me ?
All of Spain must know that !
That they're committing murder
to save the banks !
You know that sooner or later
they will throw you out of your house,
you're waiting for that moment
when they'll ring the doorbell,
showing you the papers,
telling you "in 10 days from now
you will leave this house".
So psychologically, you keep thinking
about this over and over.
People end up in depression,
they don't always end up killing themselves
but this is a serious psychological problem,
aspecially for those who have children,
and so it becomes an important social problem.
"530 property evictions a day
10 suicides a day"
"I lost my home and my job,
but I didn't loose my dignity."
"What future for our children
if our only legacy for them is misery ?"
In every job people take
cigarette breaks, right ?
This is my smoke.
A signature !
Because no one should be homeless !