Around the Guadalajará high-speed train station,
is born Valdeluz !
Linked to the transport and communication route
on which Europe's development is based,
At a high connectivity point,
A city designed for the 21st century,
with all modern services,
and with all infrastructures required for the future.
Prepared for growing.
Thought for living.
Every day your illusions colide with our illusions
A city for the future,
in which we will start living very soon.
Ciudad Valdeluz !
Start living !
Ciudad Valdeluz is not a city.
Originally built for 30.000 people, only a few
hundred families live in Ciudad Valdeluz
The promotor of the city, Reyal Urbis,
filed for bankruptcy in February 2013.
Ciudad Valdeluz has no public services.
A single bus line connects Ciudad Valdeluz
with Guadalajará, the closest city.
The golf, which is not used, is however maintened
with water from the neighboring river.
Every evening, the empty buildings are light up
to give an illusion of life.
Ciudad Valdeluz is not a city.
Ciudad Valdeluz is an illusion.