The causes of the current economic situation
are the following ones.
First a very high public deficit.
Second, the lack of competitiveness
of the Spanish economy,
which forces us to apply structural reforms.
Third, a very indebted financial system.
It is one of todays news :
the European markets are collapsing,
and among them the IBEX
which had a fall of almost 6%.
Spain asked the Euro-group
for a rescue fund for the banks.
Euro-group allowed a 100 billion euros loan.
100 billion euros. That is the maximum amount
that Europe is willing to lend to Spain
in order to save its bank sector.
After Greece, Ireland and Portugal,
it is the turn of the forth economy
of the euro zone to call for help.
Hundreds of indignants protested this Saturday
in front of the Bankia head office in Madrid,
under the slogan
"save the people, evict the bankers"
Capitalism is like a bicycle,
you have to keep pedaling
because if you stop, you'll fall.
Capitalism needs to grow in order to survive.
For 10, 15 years, capitalism had
a growth formula : the real estate bubble.
Building houses, selling houses, speculating.
We hear saying that the capitalist model
in the EU has a more productive nature
than the American one who is more speculative...
In Spain that idea should
have shocked us
because the basics of
the Spanish economic growth,
in the '90 and in the first decade of the 21st century,
were tourism and construction,
two economic sectors that are defined
by their speculative condition.
in 2007, the real estate
construction in Spain
has been equal to the total of buildings
made in France, Germany and England.
you put together all that has been built in these three countries,
you will get to the same quantity as in Spain.
There is clearly something wrong here.
The houses, the apartments
have become a financial tool.
Aspecially that the banks, as it happened
in the USA with the subprimes,
made no checking of the people
they lent money to for buying a house,
because if those people couldn't pay, the house was worthed three times
more two years after, so the bank wasn't loosing anything.
Everybody is in real estate, real estate collapses :
well, everything collapses ! It's as simple as that !
So it was not a miracle at all.
It was only an illusion.
"Trusting"
"Economic terrorism...Market dictatorship...
Politicians, puppets of the market."
"Death to the money !"
When the crisis exploded, 50% of the money
circulating in Spain was handled by the savings banks.
And the savings banks were manipulated by the politicians,
no matter the political party, left wing or right wing.
They were using savings banks to make investments
in infrastructures that made them look as the best.
They built an airport but there was
no need for an airport ! It's really crazy !
For example the airport of Ciudad Real,
next to Madrid, not far from here.
Madrid already has an airport.
Why another airport so close ?
I would understand it if it were
500 km away or 300 km...
A phantom airport ready to receive
2,5 millions of travelers a year,
that today a place of
transit for hares only.
It costed 1 billion euros,
today it is sold for 100 millions,
A tenth of what it was worthed.
Spain with 47 million inhabitants
has 52 airports.
Germany with almost twice as
many inhabitants, has only 39.
The first phase of the crisis was
when they started saying
that the problem was only related to the
savings banks not the private banks.
And we can prove that because they invested in useless airports,
useless train stations, buildings, things like that, ok, fine.
So what we have to do is make them merge.
As the savings banks can't take money
from the financial markets, the trade markets,
They said "if we convert them into anonymous
companies, into banks, it's going to be great !
Because we'll have our capital
raised by giving stocks to the public."
When Bankia was released on the market, it was really
the huge stock operation, the great example of stock exchange release.
So they convinced a whole bunch of clients
to buy Bankia's stocks. All right ?
Those clients, today, they have lost
90% of their investment.
We are now proving that the accounts
Bankia presented were wrong.
So the Spanish security exchange commission
didn't do its job.
Because its mission is to verify that
the showed data is correct. And it wasn't.
A lot of things were hidden and this had been presented
as the big restart example of the Spanish bank industry.
Bankia has a debt of over 19 billion euros.
An unprecedented loss that the company
explains by having to spend 27 billion euros
to cover for the real estate risk.
The new president of the Spanish group
Bankia shows his confidence.
Friday he asked the Spanish Government
for a record support of 19 billion euros.
Without that, the forth bank in the country,
falling under the toxic real estate assets,
would risk to contaminate the whole sector.
This public bank rescue costed 23,5 billion euros.
In Spain today, government's speech
notifies that the main problem of the economy
is the public debt,
the debt of different public services.
But 83% of the Spanish debt is private :
a debt contracted mainly by
the banks and the savings banks.
And the masterstroke here,
what I believe to be a genuine scam,
is the process of nationalization of the private debt
now going into full public ownership.
The banks, the financial institutions,
that have engaged
strictly speculative and
deeply immoral activities,
are now receiving public funds in which,
let's not forget, the EU is completely involved.
As for the private banks, the managers
weren't able to manage them,
That's a proved thing since they needed help,
I think I'm making myself clear.
Clearly, no evidence is needed,
it's just like that.
They're getting help, but the families
who were scammed,
and who don't have any means now,
they are thrown out in the street ?
That makes you want to explode !
That's not fair !
700 000 to a million people have seen
several billions of their savings evaporate.
32 billions in 2010,
in a complex financial product :
the "preferred shares",
which were never made comprehensive,
that the banks started to offer
during the economic boom.
When the real estate bubble bursted,
those shares were a fast way
for the banks to replenish their treasury
cumulate the reserves requested
by the Government and by Brussels.
The scammed clients were the old,
retired people,
that trusted the recommendations of their bank agencies
regarding the placement of their entire life savings.
Today, 300 complaints
have been filed by people
invested their savings into "preferred shares"
offered in 2009 by Bankia.
They claim their money back and
the public recognition of the scam.
It's the same policy as in Greece,
a policy that leads to economic
and social suicide.
A policy dictated by the Troïka.
the only thing the Troïka wants
is to save French and German banks.
The Spanish financial system has
a debt of 300 billion dollars
to the French and German banks.
If the Spanish financial system falls down,
that debt will never be paid.
So what the Troïka wants
is for this debt to be paid
in order to avoid
a domino effect.
Its goal is simply to give money
to the Spanish financial system,
so that the Spanish financial system
pays its debts to the French and German banks.
And as a consequence of this priority,
we have budget cuts
in the health sector, in education
and we don't fight against unemployment.
There is no fight at all.
"Murderers"
"Thieves"
"We don't owe,
we don't pay !"
"They are leaving us without a future.
There are people responsible, there are solutions."