Two suicides in less than 48h,
both in the province of Málaga.
A man and a woman took their life
after loosing their home.
Amaya Egaña was 53 years old
when she threw herself from
the forth floor of her apartment's balcony,
just when the court bailiffs
were at the building's front door.
A 40 year old man hanged himself
in his home in Barcelona
after receiving the eviction
order for unpaid rent.
It is the third death case
in less than a month,
related to the procedures
for unpaid mortgages.
This apartment is not
to be given away !
First we have to stop the eviction,
then start the battle against the bank
to get the debt canceled,
so that they don't request the rest of the debt
after having them evicted from their home.
After that, the Social Assistance has to find an alternative accommodation,
where he could stay with his daughter.
Because the bank gave Anuar a mortgage
even though they knew he wouldn't be able to pay for it.
He didn't have a payslip, nor fixed incomes,
and even so, the bank gave him the loan, when
they were only interested in granting mortgages.
They sold him a car without brakes,
they knew he couldn't handle the mortgage.
This apartment is not
to be given away !
"Los desahucios",
the property evictions.
Not a day goes by in Spain
without talking about this issue.
It became the symbol of the country's big fall
into poverty and insecurity.
Since 2007 and the beginning of the crisis,
around 500.000 people have been evicted from their homes,
for not being able the pay for the loans
they got during the real estate boom.
The banks seize the houses
and the Spaniards end up in the street.
At the PAH, the Platform
of Mortgage Victims,
a group born as a result of
the 15M meetings in 2011,
people fight day and night
against evictions.
Chema Ruiz is one of the
spokespersons of the PAH.
He contributed with his colleagues to the emersion of
a public debate regarding evictions and the Spanish mortgage law.
He doesn't hesitate to organize blocking actions
against evictions or to occupy the banks,
facing a government that turns
a deaf ear to it.
Everyday more and more people come to the platform,
and each time in a more insecure situation.
The purchasing power of people with
mortgage problems is starting to grow.
We're not talking about poor people anymore,
that no one cares about,
we're talking about people playing golf
with judges and journalists,
professions that used to have a certain purchasing power.
They had signed a mortgage according
to their past living standards,
but now the upper middle class
is starting to drown.
Neighbors !
Wake up !
They're evicting people
right next to you !
At the news they say that
they're reimbursing the banks.
I saw that the government
will give 300 millions to Bankia.
The governement should be
ashamed of that.
They get the money and they take the homes
from people who need it the most.
That's unacceptable.
what the government is doing is not fair.
How much debt do you have left ?
196.000.
I had a 205.000 debt,
I payed for it during three years,
but I mostly payed for the interests.
And now I don't know,
now that I'll give them my home,
I'll  stay with the debt...
I don't know what will happen...
Comrades, let's go downstairs,
they're here.
The bank, already ?
"Bankia cheats, scams
and leaves people without a home."
The problem is that in Spain the banks were allowed
to overestimate housings with no limits.
They were signing mortgages
based on a totally false value.
When the value of the housing starts to adjust,
it returns to its fare level.
So families who are still able to pay,
signed for a mortgage that was worth 200.000 euros
but because of the interests
it sums up to 400, 450.000 euros.
They end up paying
400, 450 000 euros
for a  property that is really
worth 70 000 today.
We will now let you
talk and ask questions.
So raise your hand and we will
pass you the microphone.
I have the following problem.
I am retired.
My retirement pension
is of 550 euros.
My appartement is now auctioned.
What do I do ?
In fact I think that
all of us present here
are condemned to loose our homes.
Besides loosing your home,
the bank is still asking
a large debt from you
because the housing is awarded for 60% of its value,
a value that they decided,
and they can also ask for
delay interests and legal costs.
We are condemned to never be able
to start over our life.
Confronted with this phenomenon,
Chema and the PAH members
plead for the transfer
in lieu of payment solution.
In fact, it would allow citizens to give their homes
in exchange for a total erase of their debts.
The government and the banks
reject this solution for now.
They told me they were
going to send the...
How is that called ?
They were going to send
the eviction order.
Yes but it hasn't arrived yet.
What a disgrace.
- That's alright...
Two ushers came to my house
telling me that I had a month
to leave the house and do all the paperwork.
Would you like to ask for
the transfer in lieu of payment ?
That means, they take the house
and they leave you alone.
- Yes...
- Or do you have another solution ?
Rent another housing?
- No, what I want
is to keep my house.
- We don't want
to loose our apartment.
It's been 4 years since he is
unemployed, we can not pay.
I don't want them to evict us...
- What about a waiting period ?
-  The bank doesn't want that ! We want...
- What bank ?
- Bankia.
Let's see if we can get you
something in exchange.
If not, you would  loose your home
and stay with 100.000 euros of debt.
They say here you have
80 000 left to pay.
Plus 40 000 of taxes.
That's 120.000 of debt.
We will see if we manage to negotiate.
If not, what you have
to do is talk to...
Where do you live ?
- La Elipa.
- Okay, in La Elipa there's a neighborhood assembly,
a group of indignants and everything.
If they don't cancel your debt,
you should see with those groups,
and give them your home, so that
someone else can occupy and live in it.
Besides meeting people
in the same situation as you,
It's very very important that you go
to the neighborhood assemblies.
There you will find people that will be there
the day of your eviction,
People that, if you want to protest
in front of your bank, they will go with you.
So if you think that your lawyer
will save you, you are wrong.
You have to mobilize yourself !
Okay ?
-  And together we are stronger !
- Let's go on with the questions...
When things are unbearable,
there are only two ways :
either we kill each other
over the miserable scraps left,
and I don't think it will be that way.
either, and I believe that, we will manage
to organize a European alternative
and change things.
The Europe of markets will become
the Europe of the People,
I am sure of that.
We don't allow
any more evictions !
...an information from the City Police,
to communicate to the national police officials,
that, apparently, and we will
confirm that in a few moments,
the judge has canceled Anuar
and his family's eviction today.
YES WE CAN !
The PAH (Platform of Mortgage Victims) received in 2013
the European Citizen Price, awarded by the European Parliament.
The members of the Popular Party have immediately denounced this decision,
accusing it of being "outrageous" and asked the Parliament to redraw it.
The property evictions are continuing.
One eviction every 15 minutes.