Ten years ago we used to talk about
the Spanish economic miracle.
Then we abruply went
from miracle to misery.
You have to mobilize yourself !
Okay ?
PUBLIC HEALTH...
… WE DON'T SELL IT,
WE DEFEND IT !
I don't think it's a crisis but a true depression
that will go beyond the one of 1929.
And that is the government's fault !
I think they are trying to dismantle
everything that has been built.
It's the same policy as in Greece,
a policy that leads to
economic and social suicide.
We must keep our strength !
We have to continue until
they ask for negotiations.
Austerity is not the only alternative.
We can't go on like this,
and people are aware of that now.
We shouldn't pay a large
part of the Spanish debt.
We don't allow any more evictions !
The crisis may be the perfect
excuse to recreate
the 19th century society,
a society of rich and poor people.
Our country is clearly going
to the Third-World.
It's a sacking, a swindle, a robbery !
Here are the options
to qualify this crisis...
In this country there is an economic crisis,
but most of all there is a political crisis.
A radical political change cannot be avoided.
The question is : how far should we go ?
No, no, no !
They don't represent us !
We haven't had this feeling
in Spain in a long time.
We felt the indignants movement
could go very far.
Neighbor !
Listen ! We are at war !
Nobody had managed to make so many different
people get out on the streets.
And the 15M did that.
This is the most
remarkable event in Spain
since the death
of Franco in 1975.
No, no, no !
We are not afraid !
If you fight,
you can loose.
But if you don't fight,
then you are lost.
It's very very important that you go
to your neighborhood assemblies.
Calling what is happening crisis
is part of the lure,
and part of the lie.