ELECTIONS : they could choose side A or side B,
but it was the same tune.
The purpose of my work
is to reinforce
the reader's opinion.
Reinforce his thought mechanisms.
Not telling him how things are,
but helping him understand
by himself.
I believe that satire today
has to keep in mind
the fact that the battle
is being fought
inside people's conscience,
more than in economy,
or ideology.
And that's where his work is
most important and most difficult too.
My name is Andrés Rábago, I am
better known as El Roto.
I draw for the press
and paint.
I don't know what this is...
One of my ways of working,
is not to think about
the real situation,
but to creat metaphors
reflecting that situation.
My work doesn't refer
to the concrete actors,
but to the philosophy, the way of thinking
and the interests behind that.
Because the actors come and go.
But the mechanisms,
they stay.
No need for your children to study,
ours are already doing it.
To downsize costs, I have
externalized my conscience.
I work a lot on my texts.
They are very elaborated,
to be very concise,
with very few words.
For technical reasons,
because the reader doesn't have
much time to read the paragraphs.
If they are very brief,
they are easier to assimilate
into our storage capacity.
Sometimes I don't even use a single word,
like in this case for example.
These drawings are more complicated to do,
because words always
make my job easier.
Aspecially in daily work, drawing without
any words would be very difficult.
Words are precious.
- What a disgrace, the markets are forcing us to apply some policies
that we already wanted to apply. - Oh my God !
The financial power works
for the political power,
just as the political power
works for the financial one.
They have the same interests.
I'm sorry my friends : social conquests
were only temporary concessions.
I think they are
trying to dismantle
everything that has been built.
Meaning that, there is a very clear ideological
component in the way of governing.
It is not so much
an economic issue,
as an ideological one.
That's not happening just in Spain.
What is happening in Spain
comes from the
anglo-saxon world,
and it is putting
Spain to the test,
but also other countries that
don't have a good ability to react.
But Spain is a
experimental zone,
the same thing will be done
in other places.
So people from other European
countries shouldn't look at us,
saying "poor people
with their problems",
because this problem
we have today,
will soon be everyone's problem
in these countries.
This is a social counter-revolution.
It is a true social counter-revolution.
We could have a different policy
but it is paid less.
This character doesn't have a face.
That financial sector without a face,
we don't know who is behind it.
Who are they ? The banks...
Who are the banks ?
It's a secret...
I represent the allegory of power
through unrecognizable people.
I am not interested in wasting paint
on them, because they are not worth it.
They are not worth the paint
or the paper I use.
What kind of financiers are they,
who need to be financed ?
To the 15M young people : found a party
and we will finance you to be just like the others.
I believe the political class is a sort of mirror
of the general situation of this country.
Politicians are not aliens,
they are born here, trained here,
and their mind is made of thoughts and moral values
that reflect the general population.
I don't think we have on one side
the corrupted political class
and on the other side the social class,
the population who is pure.
I think the responsibility
belongs to all of us.
We cannot always say
it is their fault.
I believe there is a social
responsibility in all of this.
Basically I think we refuse
to look at our own behaviors.
We look at what others do,
but we don't see what we do.
This is why I think
we need this reflection,
this critical look
on our own actions.
And my drawings are often
trying to denounce this.
Let's say I'm trying to stimulate
our capacity to analyze,
not just the external things,
but our own ways of understanding
and seeing ourselves,
so that we can take
better care of our lives.
Nothing man, nothing ! The juvenile unemployment
will be fixed with time.
Bankers
Economy
At school they teach us to read,
to write and to scour through garbage.
There is some kind of
brutality in the form,
but the content of my work
is an affectionate one.
An affectionate content behind
an appearance of coldness.
Do you remember when the world had an horizon ?
- How was it, daddy ?
The operation was a success : we managed to make it look like
a crisis, when it was actually a sacking !