Spaniards !
Franco...
...is dead.
36 years of dictatorship has ended
The 6th of December 1978,
Spaniards return to vote
to approve the new Constitution.
A military coup attempt
I have ordered
civil authorities
and all the chiefs
of the General Staff,
to take the necessary measures
in order to maintain
the constitutional order
within the law.
We organized
in transparency
the third general elections.
and more than a party's victory,
it is the victory of democracy
and of the Spanish people.
Election of the socialist
Felipe González
Official ending
the democratic transition
This country's transition period,
was presented as a democratization.
But the truth is that Franco
died in his bed.
And no true separation
of powers was made,
justice is not independent,
it is tied to the political power,
members of the General Council of Justice
are named by political parties.
Nobody went to jail for having
established this military dictatorship .
The ones in power who
defended Franco's dictatorship,
are still in power,
defending democracy.
And this is being maintained,
it is like a legacy.
So there has never been a revolution,
there has never been a break
as in other countries.
Not even as in Portugal or Greece.
We've inherited Franco's way
of making politics.
It is the same form, with corruption,
client networks, it is the same.
The Spanish Popular Party is shaking.
The so-called "bonus scandal" got to the
ruling party's head office.
Thursday, around 500 people were demonstrating
in front of the siege, on Genova street,
requesting explanations
regarding the bonus scandal,
in which several members of the Popular Party's head office,
including Prime Minister Rajoy, would be involved.
It is a corrupt, incompetent political class,
selfish...
and deceiving.
If there's really a crisis in Spain,
if there is something we can actually call crisis,
then it's a political crisis.
It is the political class
of this country
that has totally let down
the people's hopes.
In September 2011,
the Constitution was reformed.
It was the first reform since 1978,
a rushed reform, required by the European Union,
that states that
the public administration debts
towards private entities
become a priority to any
other kind of expense.
In other words,
health and education are secondary
among our government's priorities.
This reform was supported by the Popular Party,
the conservative right-wing party,
but also by the Socialist party.
I believe this explains
very well people's critical attitude
towards the Spanish
political class.
When we asked for more democracy,
we wanted to change things,
they told us, "you cannot have more democracy,
the Constitution is untouchable".
And all of a sudden one summer they changed it
so that they could pay the debt to foreign countries.
It was the exact opposite
of our request !
... first police charges.
There was a call for a protest.
1.500 anti-riot agents
are protecting the area.
We have also seen people throwing
objects to the anti-riot agents.
You can also see injured people.
I repeat, these images are live from the
Neptuno Square, right next to the Congress.
As we said, the Congress area
is totally closed off.
Yes, yes, yes !
Let's go to the Congress !
No vote ! No vote !
We are in a real mess !
With this governement !
Less police !
More education !
The Parliament and the system,
ever since the 15 of May,
have to find solutions, because everything that
was done before is over now.
No, no, no !
They don't represent us !
I think this cannot
be called democracy,
or it is a very
sick democracy,
an imitation of democracy,
a hologram that looks like democracy,
but it has so many flaws that if
you pass your hand through it,
this is the only thing you see :
a hologram, not a democracy.
Officially we are a democracy :
we can vote, we have
members of Congress,
but as citizens we cannot
decide of anything.
Citizens cannot decide
over health, education,
pensions, salaries.
These matters are being decided
by supranational institutions
like the Troïka, big companies,
the European Central Bank, rich people.
A few years ago, there was
this ironic campaign in Spain
for Emilio Botín,
the president of the Santander bank
to become directly
the Prime Minister.
Since he was already
dictating the game rules,
why continue with the
practical joke of elections ?
That ironic campaign draw clearly
the attention on a
very important issue.
In this country, that was
not industrialized,
that lost its industry
when entering the EU,
the public companies
were privatized.
The public bank was privatized.
And we remained with
this deprived State,
without any capacity
of managing economy.
And when a Prime Minister like Zapatero came
and tried to manage the crisis,
we realized we had no tools
to fight the crisis.
He could no longer
use the public bank,
use the public companies.
The only thing left
was begging the banks
to be nice to the people.
That's proof of
the lack of economic democracy
because the economic resources
are held by a minority.
And so a minority
decides of everything.
I come to this tribune to ask
for a citizen rescue plan.
A rescue plan for the people instead of
a rescue plan for the banks
as approved by this government.
Unfortunately I am doing this
from a devalued desk.
This desk here is devalued
just as this Assembly is.
This Assembly, this desk,
that used to be the symbols
of national sovereignty,
the symbols of the crystallization
of this country's dreams of democracy.
And we can say with conviction
and honesty that above all,
this was the place where people used to debate
the project of society the country wanted.
What have we left today ?
Unfortunately, all we have left is
the appearance of what it used to be.
Because we are aware that today
we are not living in a democracy,
that we don't have the tools to decide
how we want to organize our society,
because those decisions
are taken by other authorities,
to which, we citizens,
don't have access.
We have to rebuild our institutions.
And to do that
we need a new Constitution,
that gives citizens these tools.
Just like in Iceland,
a representative example,
where the citizens
have risen against
the need to save the banks
and to socialize the debt.
This is exactly what
we have to do here.
Being able to write a wiki-constitution,
just like in Iceland,
a Constitution that every citizen could
amend online, I find that genius.
But of course,
this country is a laboratory,
with 270.000 people
that practically all know each other.
They all have the
same family tree.
It's not easy to do the same
in a bigger country.
But we have
to keep that in mind.
We can no longer accept that
a citizen's only role in democracy
is putting a piece of paper
in a ballot box every four years.