We are the elderlies !
But we are not afraid !
This is our square !
You, the one looking at us !
They are stealing from you too !
I won't repay
a euro for a prescription  !
They are attacking
the middle class.
My children will loose 3.000 euros.
- Tell the story to the camera !
- 3.000 euros ! They lost their bonus.
They are civil servants.
Their bonus were not paid.
Consumption will collapse.
This is a consequence
of budget cuts.
This policy is insane
from all points of view,
because it keeps taking more and more from people.
For example, before, with my pension,
I could afford to go
to the movies, to the theater,
to dinner or just eat something out.
Now I cannot afford that anymore.
Because I have to be careful
with all the cuts in my budget.
They are liars because
they lied to the population.
Only a politician can do that.
Rajoy, resignation !
Puerta del Sol is
the main square of Madrid.
This is where the 15M was born,
where all the ideas go through,
and the Yayoflautas,
we want to be here too.
We have lost most of our rights, including liberties
that took us 40 years to obtain.
Pilar !
Every four years we vote
for political programs.
At the end they apply the contrary of what we voted for,
so there's very little democracy left.
The current government is following
a completely opposite policy
than the one they promised us
in their electoral program.
What's left of the democratic legitimacy ?
Nothing !
I think that Spaniards biggest problem
is that once we got democracy, we thought
it was for life and that's not true.
Democracy needs to be fought
for day after day.
Otherwise it gets corrupted. Like still water.
And this is what
we have in Spain today.
We're going to be famous !
In France, and everywhere else !
My name is Pilar Goytre. I am 65 years old
and I just retired.
I have three children
and three grandchildren.
I dedicate myself today
to the Yayoflautas movement.
My father was a military and my mother
didn't work, she stayed at home.
We were nine brothers and sisters
and we are all still alive.
Since we were a lot in the house,
and my father was only a military,
only the boys
got to have a career.
There was not enough money
to allow girls to have a career.
So we had to look for work.
I studied to be a secretary,
and finally things turned
out quite well for me.
The birth of Yayoflautas
was a result of the 15M movement.
We joined all
the demonstrations,
we supported the people evicted from their homes
because that's what hurts us the most.
We participated in all
the hospital gatherings.
Besides our own actions
we collaborate with those who need us.
And people ask for our
cooperation more and more !
We are just like a tank, moving slowly,
but moving, we keep moving forward…
And we are patient. We are almost all
retired so we are not in a hurry.
"GENERAL STRIKE !"
We are old !
And we are indignants !
The next unemployed
should be a Congressman !
Botella [current mayor of Madrid]
does not understand anything !
We want them to see that we,
old people, not just the 90 years old,
because some of us are 50 or 60,
we can do a lot of things.
We won't stay at home feeling
sorry for ourselves,
watching television and saying "what a disaster,
everything is falling appart, we can't do anything".
Of course we can, we can go out in the street
and fight next to those children,
put some pressure to make things better
or at least stop them from getting worst.
If you protest, the government
might say they won't give up,
they might say "we won't change anything
even if you go out in the streets",
finally they will end up
doing something.
Five years of crisis,
people can't handle this anymore.
In every family there is someone
unemployed. In every family.
And there are families
where everybody is unemployed.
And everywhere in the newspapers, on television,
they keep telling you that we have to help each other,
that social services
are offering soup kitchens,
that Caritas can't feed everybody anymore
because there's no more money.
We see that everywhere.
The Yayoflautas is a movement
of mature people,
who believe that what is happening today
in Spain is absolutely unfair.
that the society didn't cause this crisis
and that we don't have to pay for it.
There's no reason why we should loose
our social rights, because we acquired them.
We believe the crisis can be stopped in another way
and without always cutting downward.
We are ready to fight as long as
it takes to defend our rights,
and the rights of our children, and the rights of our grandchildren.
We don't want to go back to Franco's time.
We know what that means and we don't want that.
So we will fight to stop that from happening.