It is time.
It is time to bring the light
inside the cages.
To break down the walls of words
telling us that everything will be fine,
telling us that something else is impossible,
that the laws of nature made us what we are.
It is time to no longer listen to the speeches
telling us that everything is balanced,
that justice has nothing to do with this
and that there's nothing we can do about it.
We will do something about it.
The 15M movement is an awakening,
a sudden awakening,
in a time where this was absolutely necessary
because we were totally asleep.
This is the most
remarkable event in Spain
since the death
of Franco in 1975.
"We are the 99%", and that
is the key to everything.
The 15M made a difference
in history.
YES, WE CAN !
Today, we wish to put
aside our own symbols,
our own private interests,
because we wish to prove
that what joins us all
together is indignation !
Against government's abuses,
against big corporations,
against financial entities !
And most of all, we want
an unconditional democracy,
a democracy that is not reduced by an unstoppable,
dehumanized, destructive neoliberalism !
In spring 2011,
five or six major elements
were joined together
in an almost magical way.
The first, obviously,
is the crisis.
Based on this central idea
that governments were busier
helping private companies who had
speculated, than citizens.
Second element : the protests generated
by the crisis in the universities.
The Bologna Plan created
a chaos in the universities.
It is not surprising that most of the young people
camping at the beginning, were students.
Third :
the agenda of May 2011,
with some dull provincial
and mayoral elections.
That was a good opportunity
for the movement
to bring to the table
a few concealed topics.
Forth, the symbol of the Arab spring,
which I believe is more important that it seems.
Fifth and last element is the background work
done by the alternative social movements.
The 15M went out in the street
with a political claim :
"they don't represent us !"
And to me this is very important,
because it wasn't
a corporative claim saying :
"they are leaving me without a job",
or "my rights are being taken from me".
We went out in the street with the idea that
"they are calling this democracy, but this isn't one"
THEY ARE CALLING THIS DEMOCRACY,
BUT THIS ISN'T ONE !
It was a tremendous rise
of energy. Tremendous.
We knew that people were going
to respond to our call because we could feel it...
Thanks to the communication work
of over 400 groups supporting us.
I was first surprised by the
number of people present there.
Then, by the ability
of organizing things…
I found myself in a
very organized demonstration.
And then, I had the
pleasant surprise
of seeing a great diversity
of people there.
I am a teacher in a business
school, I am a liberal,
not a radical one,
not a conservative,
but I tend to be liberal.
I found myself there next to
people from anarchist movements,
next to communists...
and I dearly remember
this grandpa
who climbed onto a mailbox,
who had an old republican flag.
It seemed as if he had taken
that banner out, straight from 1935 !
I hoped he would not fall,
or he could have broken his back !
There were people of all ages,
students, from my
business school,
people from the right wing, left wing, a little bit of everything.
That really draw my attention.
Nobody had managed to make so many different
people get out on the streets.
And the 15M did that. It did it
because it made the right diagnostic.
In this country there is an economic crisis,
but most of all there is a political crisis.
There is what
Martin Luther King said.
And I believe it represents very well
what we are trying to say here.
It says  : "when we will remember
this century we are living in,
the greatest tragedy will not be
the strident clamor of the bad people,
but the appalling silence
of the good people"
When the protest was over, there were 15 people
that decided to stay at Sol.
I believe it was those people
who lighted the fuse.
After the demonstration
I stayed there with a few friends of mine.
There were many others
that wanted to continue.
So I was going around
when I heard people saying :
"Why don't we stay ?
Why don't we do something else ?"
Just as in the Tarhir Square in Egypt, we wanted
to reclaim the square or something like that.
And someone came with the idea
of camping there, on that square.
I was sitting there
and I found this idea amazing.
I joined them and I was there
when everything started
We can do the
camping here, okay?
We can't put tents, because they will probably
make us leave in two seconds.
But we can put rush mattings, cardboards
or whatever could help us hang in here...
Because the ground is hard.
Who thinks about
staying here tonight ?
Raise your hands those
of you who will stay !
Alright, there's
enough people...
Those of you who
cannot stay tonight,
but who wish to stay just a while with us
and give us strength, you are welcome.
It would be great if tomorrow,
when some of you must go to work,
others could stay
and maintain the camping.
If just a few can do that, they have
to see there is still something here,
and that we will resist
until the elections.
So, those who can stay,
come closer,
and let's organize ourselves,
we will get a few rush mattings, cardboards.
water, and anything else
we could need, okay ?
The week after, there were going
to be provincial and mayoral elections.
And then we thought : "why don't we stay here,
as a form of protest, until the elections ?"
Resist until the day of the elections.
Make as much noise as possible,
bring as much people here as possible
so that it won't be just one demonstration like today.
Resist and create a movement...
Now we have to decide what
we are going to do while we are here,
some people have already
made some suggestions......
First how will we organize ourselves, and then
think at... Most of all, what is our manifest ?
First it was an exciting moment.
But obviously as we were very few
to stay there the first night,
we didn't really know where all this could lead us
and what consequences it could have.
So it was simply like "a new action, a new thing
is happening, how exciting  !"
and we were very focused on how to
organize it so that it would continue.
We call people to join this mobilization
starting from this moment.
Don't wait for tomorrow,
just come now.
And for other cities to take
their squares and do the same.
From the very first night,
when we joined together
and we started to write a manifest,
when we payed for the webpage
and we started to publish things online,
we payed right away
for the international domain names,
thinking that if this would work,
we had to spread it out everywhere.
just as it got to us from the Arab spring,
the Icelandic revolution or other movements..
The global aspect has always been very important,
this movement is not a local one
just about our country in today's moment,
it is a universal movement.
To all the people in all the countries.
We're truly opening this to everyone.
It's the first time that this
assembly has so many participants.
First of all, we will
establish this day's agenda.
Then we will have a review of the different
commissions that have been working,
then we will see if we
should set up the tent.
"Do not stand there watching us, inform yourself,
you too are concerned"
Several commissions were organized
to discuss different topics.
People started to think about topics
and suggest several matters
related to a social change.
It's like starting
all over again :
"now we are all here, we are all sick
of everything, we need to do something,
the first thing we will do
is to talk to each other,
and express what we want".
So the movement started mostly with this,
with talking, with the assembly.
It was clear from the start,
and no one argued about it,
that it was going to be an horizontal movement,
meaning that everyone had to speak ,
and everyone would be
the leader of this movement.
We couldn't have imagined the support we were going to have
and the consequences of this movement.
For the few of us that were here last night,
we feel a bit overwhelmed.
So what I mean is that yesterday
we thought that setting up a tent was stupid,
but today it truly makes sense.
It will draw people's attention
and it will make more people come.
NO TO VIOLENCE !
When they evicted us, the second night,
the police wrecked everything.
We then made an announcement asking people
to come back to the square at 8 p.m,
to camp here again and again,
for as long as it would take.
And a crowd of people came and then
it became this craziness we know.
From that point, it really started to be... something different.
And then we really felt that
it could spread to anywhere.
This is far more than
a concentration of people !
This is an assembly !
An assembly means
we are all together !
We are many !
Far more than
what we had imagined.
Until now we stood
our ground at Sol !
We got organized in groups
and in working commissions.
We have two very important questions
that we would like to ask you all, okay ?
First of all :
do we want to stay
here tonight ?
All of a sudden everything
had changed,
society, politics,
everything !
From one day to another, everything
had changed or was about to change.
We are convening an assembly
tomorrow, and the day after,
and every day
after that, at 8 p.m.
Every evening 30.000 people were coming
to the square spontaneously.
We made a call and invited people to come
but there was no logistics to organize them,
nor an official announcement made by
big organizations, nothing.
We had just told them
to come and they came,
they wanted to come and they were
staying there for hours,
Nothing concrete was happening,
but they just wanted to be there,
to be a part of all this.
Thousands of citizens, and more every day,
have taken the square for four consecutive days.
As you can see and hear,
Puerta del Sol is a hive of activity.
The so called "indignants" of Madrid
assured that they would stay
there as long as necessary.
Everyone kept coming and
offering their services.
"I want to be a part of this"
"I am a dentist, so I will treat
people's teeth for free".
another said : "I am a masseur,
I will give massages",
"I am an electrician, I can help
you connect the electric wires".
Everybody was finding something to do
just to be part of it.
And then the energy was endless.
There was no way to stop it.
We haven't had this feeling
in Spain in a long time,
of being sick of everything,
of being  joined together.
But with no violence.
And in a very open way.
The place was covered
by placards with messages !
Thousands of placards where people
had written their own claims or ideas.
Seeing this was amazing.
Making people  all of a
sudden understand
how the electoral system works,
well that's a victory.
In order to change things
you have to understand them first.
People in Spain no longer see politics
the same way since the 15M.
They now see it
in a totally different way.
We can consider the 15M
as a sort of popular university.
They've managed to make people discuss
politics and economy in the street,
assemblies that took place
in the public squares.
And that is the purpose,
the 15M should not become a political party.
It's making people
aware of the truth.
All of a sudden everybody
was talking politics, everywhere.
You walked in the street
and you heard people talking about it.
Thousands of people talking about
the Electoral law for example, about referendums…
It was something new and special !
They are doing something that has
never been done in the world.
Passively, in a democratic way,
without making problems,
and without any intervention
of the police.
This is the movement's great success :
giving to older people,
and to people of my age,
the feeling that
everything was not lost.
The 15M had become
the center of everything.
All the news headlines
were focused on it !
Newspapers seem
upset when we don't do anything,
because they are selling less !
And these statistics...
80% of the population were supporting
the 15M and the whole movement.
I think this is a
very important thing.
I would like to tell you all
that you have brightened my life.
I was very miserable and all of this here
is very important to me. I love you all !
We will now begin with
the general assembly of Madrid.
The general assembly is an organism
that takes part in all decisions,
an organism in which
we all participate,
but we have to be very clear about
what our state of mind will be here.
If we agree on a proposal,
we will applaud like this.
This gesture is a veto.
A veto is a very powerful
tool in an assembly.
A member of an assembly can use his
right of veto three or four times.
So that nobody here
abuses of this right,
unless they have a radically
opposed opinion.
The formal aspect is very essential.
So that people can rethink everything,
and that everything is open
to discussion and to change.
This distinguishes us from
any political party, from organized,
vertical institutions, where changing things
is much more difficult.
At first, the 15M was mostly a methodological movement
that was asking for a change of methods.
Whether you are right wing,
left wing or a liberal :
in fact we were all demanding an improvement
of the way our society was administrated.
From my point of view,
this is what the movement was asking for.
When it moved to the street,
and the assemblies started,
it lost part of its methodological aspect
and it turned more into an ideological movement,
focused on left-wing suggestions,
that can be a good or bad thing
but that don't suit everybody.
In the campings or the assemblies,
you stop seeing
liberal and right-wing people.
They were almost rejected.
Even if it was not said,
the environment was hostile to them.
There's a part of the movement that believes
in the representative democracy, the liberal democracy,
that accepts the parliamentary logics,
that believes it's important to reform
the Spanish electoral system, so unfair.
There is a second position of those
who defend the participative democracy,
that accept how the liberal democracy orks,
but believe new elements have to be implemanted
in order to revive
this dying democracy :
participative budgets,
frequents referendums…
And there is a third position that defends
direct democracy, non delegated,
that considers that the main mission
of this movement is to define independent spaces,
so that the self managing assembly rules everything,
without any external representations.
I am not in a position to say
which one of these has the greatest echo.
But I do believe it is the third one
that makes this movement singular.
We went beyond the forecasts
of participation in the neighborhoods.
Welcome comrades !
From Villa Verde, welcome...
From Malasaña...
Comrades from Columbia, welcome !
A comrade representing...
The camping itself
didn't have a way out.
It was impossible to stop this.
To go where ?
We are camping here and now what ?
The way out were neighborhoods.
The assembly moved into the neighborhoods,
which makes even more sense to me
because your daily life is in your neighborhood,
in your home,
in the places you shop,
in the parks you go to.
And in the end this was the final
purpose of all this movement :
taking part in democracy,
the participative democracy,
deciding things
that affect us all.
It's been three weeks since
we've been here. In Madrid !
In Puerta del Sol, in the heart of the state,
in the heart of this city.
Camping is a tool.
It's a work tool,
it's not an end in itself.
It's obvious camping was
a good work tool for this movement.
Now it is time to end this camping
and work in the neighborhoods of Madrid !
The assemblies have reduced since then.
There are 30, 40 people now.
Today if you compare an assembly to one
from 2011 you can see a big difference.
Because we evolve
and we learn,
we are learning about
this new democratic culture.
Still, we didn't go
very far on some points.
For example, the internal way
of functioning was through assemblies.
But these assemblies
lacked of imagination.
Only a limited number of people
could participate, 1.000 people, maybe more,
but there was no way 10.000, 100.000
or 200.000 could participate.
But we want to reach
those level of participation,
because we want to redefine
everything, redefine the State.
So if we are 50 million people
to speak, how do we do that ?
I think we have to take the power.
Said like this, it might make you smile.
But we need to do it in a horizontal way.
Find a sort of horizontal organization,
that could integrate
the electoral game.
If we manage not to fall
into despair and sadness,
then we will clearly make a change
and create something unbelievable.
The 15M movement cannot die
because it's combat is structural.
Squares can be empty, but this state of mind
is still there and the 15M is still there !
As the crisis keeps getting worst,
the 15M will evolve in different ways.
And this is obviously
something very important.
Despite the fact that the government
uses police repression
to change people's frustration
into resignation,
the 15M cannot be crushed
by the government.
It will always be there in a latent form, and those
who are opposed to a radical change are wrong.
Because the radical
change is inevitable.
The greatest victory is making
people realize that
if you fight,
you can loose.
But if you don't fight,
then you are lost.
No one will be surprised not to know
anymore what happened to you, or to me.
No one will be surprised to see two faces merging when they gaze
into the same glass wall, in the same spring.
And this might bring relief, this might create in other cities,
in other times, euphoria and youth.
This might be a founding reason
for others to come closer together.
We will think of the loved ones,
and at the shedded tears.
We will think of the last disagreements,
of the hard words stuck in our throats,
and we will have the last word.
Ah comrade, don't try to give up your soul,
it would be too heavy to give up anyway.
With all of its secrets, your soul of revolt,
nobody would want it anyway.
It is too painful, your soul of a thousand wholes,
of a thousand bumps and of a thousand bruises.
It's yours to change
into a landscape.
Spring is still here.