My name is Leo Bassi. I come from an old circus family
and I am very proud of that.
I have many nationalities
as all the circus people.
I am proud to be 60 years old,
and still be able to laugh
about everything, as I am a clown.
In fifteen years, I've worked
ten seasons in this theater...
And this is my special meditation
corner before the show.
I actually love the fact that this theater
presents many other shows.
Some days it accomodates four shows
one after another, in the afternoon,
in the evening, then in the second evening
and sometimes late at midnight, for special events.
There are sets stored everywhere, there isn't
enough space for the dressing room,
but still making the effort to stay
independent, refusing any grants.
And satisfy the public's need for a completely
independent space of artistic creation.
I find that extremely
courageous nowadays.
Yes, the conditions are precarious, the theater
is close to being dirty but it's for a good reason.
I would rather be in a theater with dirty,
precarious dressing rooms but that takes risks,
than in another theatre with beautiful dressing rooms,
where everything is perfect but where in reality,
it's only a commercial operation
to make the public come and pay,
and what happens on stage, and the meaning
of the work are secondary.
Oh, five minutes left...
I am an agitator
and a happy clown.
Because it's been fourty years...
Fourty years !
that I try to fuck the
power in my shows.
No matter the power !
Political, spiritual, economic.
It's like a deep
need inside of me.
And I am happy at this moment,
because I noticed that something
was happening in society.
I sensed a true lack
of respect of the people,
towards the institutions.
Bankers, politicians,
even religious people  :
they are no longer
respected at all.
And that makes me happy !
When I was 16, 17, I was lucky
enough to be in Paris in May 68.
And the months after that,
the spring...
My teenage memories from that time,
are very much a reflection of what a lot of people
here in Spain are living today.
That same electric feeling that
something new is about to be created,
that feeling that we don't need
to learn from the past anymore.
By learning I am talking about the references
we have regarding the rules of living, well all that has fallen.
And so there's a great liberty,
the feeling that we're creating a new world !
To be clear,
anything can happen tonight.
Even a violent reaction
against the public.
But just to keep things clear,
as I told you,
no matter what I do,
I only do it with love.
I deeply love you !
I'm not doing it
to be aggressive,
I only want to give
you some adrenaline.
I know I find myself in a time of great transition,
and that's such a pleasure !
It's extremely rewarding to live at a time
where everything is insecure,
where many great
conversations are being...
... of being able to assist to those great conversations
that will define the next century.
All this is good. And we can
feel the energy in the streets.
Oh, so many memories...
Do you know what
happened in here ?
In 2006, the 1st of March,
and I didn't invent that,
right here, five meters
away, someone,
or some people, because the police
is still looking for the portraitures,
someone put a kilo
of explosive with gasoline,
trying to burn down the
whole theater, and to kill me,
and to kill a lot of people at the same time.
This is not a joke.
It happened during the show "The revelation",
where I was talking about my atheism,
and some people in Spain
didn't like that.
I have been to many meetings, I have listened a lot,
I have participated and I have spoken also.
And in my opinion, the level
of discussions was high.
I had the feeling that what was
being said were not ordinary.
Everybody was sitting at Puerta del Sol
but talking about fundamental things !
A place which, only a few weeks earlier,
was full of L'Oreal publicities,
of hamburgers and a few tourists shops
selling fans with bulls on it,
that was Puerta del Sol
for many years !
And I was an old man there,
they were all 25, 30 years old.
And I believe they were listening to me
a little bit like Indians in the Indian movies,
there's the ancient wise men council, the young people come
with the ideas and the old ones are just behind them.
So I played this part of the wise man,
searching and questioning their system.
How can we accuse the 15M movement
of not having a bigger success,
when the rest of the society
is even worst ?
I have always tried to open
consciousness about political issues.
For example many years ago, I started my own war
against the multinational corporations.
The idea that a multinational can fire you,
destroy the middle class.
And the difficulty is to make people
understand this political concept,
this rational concept
but in a sensual way.
How can I scare people
with a multinational ?
How to make people feel
this threat inside them ?
There is an opposition against Merkel today,
so you'll find posters of Merkel dressed up like Hitler.
All this is nothing else but a sign
of something much deeper :
what does being Mediterranean mean ?
The fact that this Mediterranean world,
and the Italian world that I know perfectly,
believes to be basically superior
to the North, because we are so called,
more sensual, more in close contact, with a more sensual
intelligence and education, or at least we think so.
But the Mediterranean world cannot
enter the North way of living.
So the question is : is the euro sustainable
if it represents two entirely different cultures ?
Can Europe exist if Bruxelles represents two opposite cultures
that have been enemies for centuries, for thousands of years ?
All this is being decided now,
here in the streets.
We know that somehow being
Mediterranean means human contact,
being together, sitting and talking
over coffee, that's very Mediterranean.
Working in a factory and not talking
to your colleague, doing this all day long,
that was in the industrial civilization,
that wasn't Mediterranean.
This is on my mind 24/7 :
what's the difference, how can this Mediterranean world
enter into a new technological society
that's discovering itself ?
Just to tell you that we are here !
All together, OK ?