21 Calle del Pez,
in the center of Madrid.
This is where the Patio Maravillas is.
Literally : the Court of Miracles.
Since the 15th of May 2011 this building has become
a meeting point for the indignant nebula,
and one of the largest
squats of the capital.
Valentin, a young 21 years old French is one of the
founders of the "Juventud sin Futuro" group,
"Youth with no future".
A group that participated actively to the 15M movement.
We truly became a public platform
at the begining of 2011.
And we did our first demonstration
on April 7, 2011.
To us, that was truly the moment
Juventud sin Futuro was born.
Being born in the street
it's what mattered most to us.
When we called for this demonstration, we were
40 maybe 50 people in Juventud sin Futuro.
And by the end of the demonstration
we were 7.000 people,
which might seem even ridiculous today
regarding the protests Spain has seen lately.
But you must know that the protest and mobilization
landscape in Spain was completely deserted.
Which means that a 2.000 people demonstration
was a successful one at that time.
From that point, JSF became a reference
to a movement that was being built.
This protest was organized by different groups
of students and people in a precarious situation.
We called people through social networks,
through Facebook, through Twitter.
We got an answer to it
and the answer is this protest.
We have to use the potential of these networks,
just as it was shown in other countries.
Our first slogan was
"A youth without a house, without a job,
without a pension, without a future but a youth with no fear ".
That was mainly the idea we were trying to bring,
that the situation for the youth was, and keeps being disastrous,
we have very few rights, very few possibilities,
which means we have no future.
But we wanted to show something
positive for the future,
that's why we said "with no fear". We're not afraid
and we will fight to make things change.
Juventud Sin Futuro takes actively
part in the 15M mobilizations.
But the group also tries to defend
Spanish youth's rights,
more and more insecure
aspecially in the work sector.
This is precisely the "Oficina Precaria's" goal,
an alternative to the traditional unions, created by JSF.
We could file a complaint saying that
you are an intern, but you are actually working,
saying they forced you to register at the university
while you are actually doing real work.
- If we file that complaint, in the best case scenario,
can we make them recognize my work retrospectively ?
- Exactly. Retrospectively, it means you should
receive the salaries they haven't paid you,
based on the minimum interprofessional wage,
or conventionnal wage.
for the past year, because you have
one year to claim unpayed salaries.
We'll stay in contact with you and we'll include
your case into a larger campaign,
where we'll regroup other cases like yours
in order to have better chances to pressure them.
What we want is to avoid others
from being in this situation,
because it is a form of violation
of the Spanish labour rights.
The minimum wage is
a little above 400 euros.
Most of the young people that find a job do less hours,
they obviously don't do 8h/day.
There are a lot of part-time contracts
where they get 300, 200 euros,
which is not enough to pay your rent,
your life, your college.
My mother still supports me,
by giving me 200, 250 euros a month.
Aside from that I work, I do French tutoring
that I obviously don't declare.
That's another reality in Spain. There are a lot
of jobs like this, totally insecure,
that are undeclared.
That doesn't even mean they forget about your rights.
No, it means, you don't have any rights.
You don't have any rights, you don't pay taxes,
so forget about retirement pension.
Maybe some people still think
they will get a retirement pension in ten years...
Well... I work undeclared by doing French tutoring,
by doing whatever I find here and there,
and maybe I add 100, 150 euros to my
monthly budget, something like that.
Do the math, that makes 350, 400 euros a month,
and with all this I cannot live and pay for a home,
as a result it's been a year since
I've decided to occupy.
Moving into empty buildings.
Occupying.
This is a common
practice today in Spain,
in a country where there are
thousands of abandoned buildings.
For many young people or entire families
evicted from their homes,
this is a last chance solution.
"Freeing the space", according to the Spanish expression,
is also a new way of bonding and redefining solidarity.
I don't think the solution is going up in the mountains
to raise goats with two coats and one pair of boots.
But I do think the true solution
is sharing everything we can have,
everything we own, everything we create,
everything we know.
That means creating common goods in a place
where the State doesn't do anything.
- Would you call yourself optimistic about the future ?
- It's pretty hard to answer.... I think it depends on the moment.
Sometimes I am filled with optimism,
and sometimes I feel as if I were touching the bottom.
I think it would be very difficult now
to destroy what the 15M has managed to do.
To kill 15M 's victories, because I think that...
the political elites have tried to suffocate the 15M.
I think that's not possible anymore because
people are already following that movement,
they are determined and
they will now seek solutions.
And if the institutional way doesn't give any solution,
they will create their own.