Nineteen... seventy... five.
My name is Inmaculada Pascual, I  teach German
at the Official Foreign Language School, in Madrid.
We always had a lot of students but now there are
more applications than what we can handle.
In fact, the requests have increased so much,
that we cannot accept anyone else.
Last year we had 74% more applications
than the year before.
Nineteen... Ninety… nine.
And this year ?
Two... thousands... eleven.
I'm Jesús, I am 25 years old,
I am an engineer in telecommunications
and I study German because
I need to find work abroad.
I'm not from Madrid,
I'm from another city, Murcia.
Because of the crisis, there's very little work
and I already had to come to Madrid to find a job.
Since there are less and less oportunities here,
I know I have to go abroad.
More out of need
than out of pleasure.
In Holland, Germany, England,
there are far more opportunities.
In our department, we receive
work offers from Germany.
They are looking for people in Spain
that could work in Germany, professionals.
Before, those who emigrated were
workers with no qualification.
But now, the well trained
people are leaving,
Spanish engineers are valued
there, doctors, nurses.
I am a nursing auxiliary.
Does you like that ?
- How did you say ?
Does ? Did ?
Which verbs can't we
be wrong about ?
This one among others...
The auxiliary verbs.
Never. So how does it go ?
Do you like that ?
Where does...
Mrs Bayer come from ?
The Sneider family
have two children.
I'm Patricia, I'm 26 years old
and I'm an engineer in telecommunications.
I'm a PHD student
and I would like to continue in Spain,
but I guess it's going to be difficult
because research is not valued here.
So I think my future is abroad.
For a young person
that just graduated,
if it's in the technical field,
engineering or something like that,
you might have a possibility in Madrid,
or Barcelona, or Bilbao.
But only as a temporary worker,
with a provisional contract
and a small pay compared
to all the years of study.
And only if you're lucky !
But in most cases,
you won't find anything in Spain.
If you get to work in Germany
for a pizza delivery service,
you have to understand what they're saying
so you don't make mistakes.
- Pizza Express, good evening !
- Good evening, it's Lisa. I would like ten pizzas, please.
- Lisa ? Can you repeat that ?
- Lisa Neumun
- And where do you live Lisa ?
- In Bonn, obviously !
- Yes, in Bonn obviously.
But what is your adress ?
- Beethoven Street 9
- Ok, so you would like a pizza ?
- No ! Ten pizzas ! So five pizzas n°6
and five pizzas n°12.
Unfortunately, there's an entire
generation, maybe mine and the one after,
that has to go abroad, because there are
a lot of well trained people,
but there is not enough work for everyone.
So most of us must go away.
Some will want to do it,
others will have to.
They know how things are, but I don't
see them sad or disappointed.
These people are fighters,
I see people that fight.
So they are not afraid to pack their things,
do an Erasmus if they can,
or go to Germany
to study German,
find a job possibility there,
a small job and then stay there.
I had students that went there
for a month and then stayed.
But then it's true that when
they can, people come back.
Their hope for the future
is to come back in Spain.
The rate of unemployment for people
under 25 years old exceeds 56%.
In 2012, 200 000 Spaniards
have left the country.