"Football is so unfair !"
"And this is one of the
unfairest game I have ever seen..."
The role of football in Spain, and I'm not talking
about sports in general, is crucial.
In France, and not even in Italy, could you imagine
the importance of football in Spain.
SPAIN IS THE WORLD CHAMPION !!!!
My name is Javier Gómez, I am the host of a daily
sports program in Spain, on the Sexta TV channel.
I used to be a Spanish football specialist
for French TV for many years.
And now I work on the Spanish
football in my country, Spain.
We have heard a lot about
the real estate bubble in this country.
The exact same thing
happened in football.
The bubble has clearly exploded.
A team like Málaga, in the Champions League,
with a Qatari owner, an emir just like
the PSG that brought a lot of money,
has difficulties paying the players.
But that didn't just happen to Málaga,
it happened to Rayo Valecano,
last year it happened to Santander
that was downgraded,
it happened to Sporting de Gijón,
and it happened to many other clubs.
It happened to Levanté, that is
in the Europa League today .
The transfer of Gareth Bale
to Real Madrid is a fact,
according to the announcement made
this Wednesday by COPE radio channel.
The Spanish club agreed with Tottenham
to have the player transfered for 99 million euros.
Three million more than what
Cristiano Ronaldo had costed.
The Spanish football has lived
above its means.
When we compete with someone, we are influenced
by what our competitor does.
Here, Real and Barça create
a huge inflation in the football sector.
Even Valencia and Atletico de Madrid...
So the salaries are totally crazy !
This sort of competition heads us
straight to disaster :
"we pay more, we pay the players more,
we have to pay more for those players !"
But how do we do that ?
We borrow money.
Why do we receive the money ? Because the institutions,
the banks, everybody wins, it's football !
If the bank finds the money for a new stadium,
they will win a lot so they lend you money to buy a player.
We start having players bought by investment
funds from the tax heavens. It happened to Saragossa.
The football sector is in the same financial craziness
that led Spain at the depths of despair.
There are more and more people
today that seek work abroad.
In the football sector
we clearly have a brain drain.
The biggest star in Manchester City
is a Spaniard.
The biggest star in Liverpool
today is a Spaniard.
And it goes on : in Chelsea, Manchester United,
Juventud, we see Spaniards everywhere.
Even the humble Spaniard, the basic football player
that usually finds a place in second division,
or in the worst teams of first
division, is leaving too.
In Greece there are fourty Spanish players ! Fourty !
And we are talking about Greece...
In Cyprus they have Spanish players,
in Russia they have more and more also.
Not only are the middle level
players leaving,
But there is a third category of
emigrants : the coaches !
Where is Unayemeri ?
Spartak, Moscow.
Where is Garrido, Vila Real's
coach last year ? Bruges, Belgium.
We have plenty of cases like this.
I read today that Greece is not going to send its
swimming team to the European Championship in France,
because they don't have enough money
to pay for the plane tickets.
For these less popular sports,
the situation is scary .
But let's take the important sports, like handball.
France is very good in handball, but more importantly
France has a very good national team,
the French championship isn't very good.
Germany and Spain have the most important
championships in the world.
Well, today, handball is dead in Spain.
Most teams can't pay the salaries.
Same story for volleyball : only one team
can go to the European championships
because all the others cannot
pay their plane tickets.
Will football find itself in a similar situation ?
I don't believe so.
Because it generates a lot of money,
for televisions for example.
But the future is scary.
For football too.